<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Yes, This Is Ian Stevens</title><link href="http://istevens.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://istevens.github.io/feeds/daily250.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://istevens.github.io/</id><updated>2016-08-29T14:58:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>First post</title><link href="http://istevens.github.io/daily250/first-post.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-08-29T14:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ian Stevens</name></author><id>tag:istevens.github.io,2016-08-29:daily250/first-post.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past April I ended a contracting gig I'd been on for two-and-a-half years
so that I could spend the summer with my then six-month-old son. Around the
same time, I bought a compact mirrorless digital camera to supplement my hefty
and neglected DSLR. After daily practice with my new camera, I decided to
continue the trend and try to take at least one picture every day. Several
months later, I'm still on track and my photography is much-improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I wondered which other activity could benefit from daily
practice. Writing seemed like an obvious choice, requiring limited tools and a
small time commitment. My daily writing regimen has three restrictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write and publish at least 250 words on a topic decided that day,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write with limited &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006s5dp"&gt;repetition and deviation&lt;/a&gt; from the topic, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with my photography, I want to create good pieces, but good pieces every day
is not a requirement. Most of what I write will be absolute garbage, as
evidenced by this first post. Most people reading my writing won't find it
interesting. That's OK, I'm not writing for them —&amp;nbsp;I'm writing for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope is that writing will become easier and more enjoyable. As a child I was
fond of writing, but these days my writing is limited to business contexts and
trying to cram thoughts into &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/istevens"&gt;140 characters on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. Fun, sometimes, but not expressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's hoping that future attempts don't need sentences like these to pad out
the length requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>