<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Yes, This Is Ian Stevens</title><link href="//istevens.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//istevens.github.io/feeds/daily250.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//istevens.github.io/</id><updated>2016-09-02T15:34:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Over twenty years on, why I still code HTML</title><link href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/over-twenty-years-on-why-i-still-code-html.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-09-02T15:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ian Stevens</name></author><id>tag:istevens.github.io,2016-09-02:daily250/over-twenty-years-on-why-i-still-code-html.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This 250-word a day blog is currently powered by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator for blogs. As with the vast
majority of blog software, Pelican lets you select themes for your site. Dozens
of themes are available, written by other Pelican users. You can also write
your own theme, which is what I chose to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would I do this? Why would I voluntarily decide to create work for myself,
use my precious free time to bang out template code and HTML, all while relying
on technical documentation which, based on my experience using free software,
is likely to be poorly-written and incomplete? Good question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been typing words enclosed in angle brackets for almost as long as
graphical web browsers have been parsing them. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ncsa.illinois.edu/enabling/mosaic"&gt;Mosaic browser&lt;/a&gt; was released in early 1993; I
wrote my first HTML tag likely in late 1994 or early 1995. HTML has been a
staple in my language stack longer than any other language I've used. The only
other technology which even comes close is shell scripting, although I've
switched shell languages several times over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large part of why I still code HTML is control. I need to know that web sites
which carry my name have &lt;em&gt;the best HTML&lt;/em&gt;. I respect bandwidth, so HTTP payloads
served by my sites need to be slim. I respect document semantics, so HTML my
sites serve needs to reflect the nature of the content. Many web sites, even
simple blogs, force far too much data on end users, and often include
JavaScript which slows page processing and rendering. Many themes for web
content use outdated semantics for content (like nested &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt; tags instead
of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;section&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;article&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt; tags). These things matter to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My web properties are an online extension of myself and should reflect my
aesthetic. I fully expect anyone looking to evaluate me on a technical level
— such as potential employers — to view source on my online offerings to do so.
Although I am well over a decade removed from having HTML in my job
description, for whatever reason I think it matters that I get my hands dirty
once in a while for everyone to see. I should probably let go of that.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Digital cameras I have owned</title><link href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/digital-cameras-i-have-owned.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-09-01T14:14:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ian Stevens</name></author><id>tag:istevens.github.io,2016-09-01:daily250/digital-cameras-i-have-owned.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/film-cameras-i-have-owned.html"&gt;I've owned at least three film cameras&lt;/a&gt; in my life, and four digital cameras in
the past fifteen years. This is the nature of digital. Film cameras can remain
useful until they break, yet a digital camera will likely lose its usefulness
once it lags behind cameras new to the market. Every digital camera I have
owned still works, yet they are no longer &amp;quot;useful&amp;quot; to me. Arguably film cameras
are useless in their inconvenience, although they still have use as niche or
retro tools. An old digital camera may produce unacceptable pictures, while
an old film camera can still produce images of acceptable quality, but which
take more effort to develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought my first digital camera, a Panasonic Lumix DMC-FZ20, in the mid 2000s.
Clunky by today's standards, I chose this quasi-DSLR as a starter camera to
introduce me to digital images. The lens was fixed, and the camera sensor was
inadequate with darker indoor shots, but it was my primary camera for several
years. I can't say that I loved this camera. As times its performance in low
light frustrated me, but I made it work. I was able to add some filters using
an extension which attached to the lens, but that was the limit of my
personalization. Eventually I gave the Lumix to a sister-in-law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first DSLR was a Nikon D80, which I bought second-hand off of a friend of
mine. Although I was able to make use of multiple lenses for the first time
since my Pentax SLR, I only bought and used two lenses: a sharp 50mm f1.8
Nikkor lens, and a Tamron zoom lens. I was finally able to experiment with
depth-of-field again. The Nikkor sharpness spoiled me though, and I rarely used
the zoom as it was too bulky for everyday use. I loved this camera, so much so
that when it suddenly stopped working after a year, I paid about as much to
repair it as I did to buy it used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all the cameras I have owned, the Nikon D80 truly introduced me to &lt;em&gt;serious
photography&lt;/em&gt;. It was better for indoor shots than my Lumix, and the Nikkor 50mm
lens I used was my best lens since the one I used with my Pentax SLR. I really
was in heaven, especially after the birth of my daughter, who provided me
with plenty of opportunities for great pictures. At some point I grew tired of
the D80, and taking it out for pictures became a chore. As with my Lumix, I
found myself pushing against the limits of what the D80 could do. While better
in low-light, indoor photography, particularly in the darker winter months, was
often lackluster. Most importantly, the D80 was too cumbersome and noticeable
for candid shots, which is likely why I eventually stopped using it outside of
special events, outdoor shots, and vacations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fill in where the D80 couldn't go, I bought a Lumix point-and-shoot. It
could fit in a pocket and took decent pictures. Focusing was often slow,
though, and this camera was more utilitarian than a love-affair. Let us not
speak of it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings me to my most recent camera, an Olympus OM-D E-M10. I could easily
write an entire post on how it has changed my photography. Size-wise,
the E-M10 fits between my first black plastic film camera and my Lumix FZ20.
This makes it extremely portable, and I think nothing of carrying it even when
running errands. I have used it for only four months, and have taken at
least one picture every day. A huge selling feature for me is the ease at which
I can use manual lenses. Although I tried attaching a manual lens to my Nikon
D80, the resulting image looked like one produced by a toy camera. I use a
different lens on the Olympus every few days, and have only had positive
experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll write more about my recent photographic experience, but this wraps up my
catalog of cameras I have owned, at least for a few more years.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Film cameras I have owned</title><link href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/film-cameras-i-have-owned.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-08-31T14:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ian Stevens</name></author><id>tag:istevens.github.io,2016-08-31:daily250/film-cameras-i-have-owned.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I really need a list of topics to write about for days when I don't know what
to write — days like this one. Let's continue with &lt;a class="reference external" href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/why-i-enjoy-taking-pictures.html"&gt;yesterday's topic of
photography&lt;/a&gt;, something which I
do every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had my own film camera when I was about 8. It was a black plastic 35mm
point-and-shoot, a real beauty, with manual advance and rewind crank. I liked
the rewind crank, which was a satisfying end-of-roll ritual. Automatic rewind
mechanisms just aren't as fun. There's still the satisfaction of a finished
roll but less direct involvement, less anticipation; just push a button.
Of course, you can never finish a roll on a digital camera; there's no notion
of being &amp;quot;done&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="idea container"&gt;
Here's an idea: Design a digital camera or app with a configurable &amp;quot;roll&amp;quot;
size, and don't allow the user to review pictures until the roll is done and
they turn a physical or virtual crank. This way, the photographer can be
more focused on taking the shots without breaking flow, and can self-impose
a goal without having to keep track of the number of photos taken.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second camera was an ugly, light grey, brick of a point-and-shoot, with a
sliding lens cover, automatic advance, push-button rewind, and flash. I don't
remember this camera as fondly as my first one. I must have treasured it as I
remember being quite upset when the case cracked after the camera fell to the
sidewalk on a trip to Montreal. This camera lasted me into university, where it
was was only used at parties and other events where I didn't want my SLR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, my first SLR. My father bought me a Pentax 35mm SLR with a 50mm lens
for a birthday when I was in second or third year of university. Many shots I
took were out of focus, but this was the camera which introduced me to
photography as a practice, not just as a means of capturing images. In
retrospect, I'm fairly certain I had no idea how to properly expose a frame for
the shot I wanted. Instead, I blindly followed the internal light meter. I
bought a bulky low-end Sigma zoom lens for versatility, but I never truly
explored the 50mm lens until very recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings me to &lt;a class="reference external" href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/digital-cameras-i-have-owned.html"&gt;my first digital cameras&lt;/a&gt;, something which I'll complete in a
later post.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Why I Enjoy Taking Pictures</title><link href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/why-i-enjoy-taking-pictures.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-08-30T11:48:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ian Stevens</name></author><id>tag:istevens.github.io,2016-08-30:daily250/why-i-enjoy-taking-pictures.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/first-post.html"&gt;yesterday's inaugural post&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned
photography:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[…] I bought a compact mirrorless digital camera to supplement my hefty and
neglected DSLR. After daily practice with my new camera, I decided to
continue the trend and try to take at least one picture every day. Several
months later, I'm still on track and my photography is much-improved.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been taking pictures since I was perhaps 8. The exact age I received
my first camera — a black plastic 35mm point-and-shoot — escapes me, but I
distinctly remember a few shots I took at the time. In one, I've directed
someone to shoot me with my hand extended along a wall to a patch of sunlight.
In another, my sister stands with one of our cats. A series of photos shows my
bike and bikes of friends decorated for a contest at the Uxbridge Fall Fair.
We're all still in elementary school in the pictures, probably grade 3 or 4.
Clearly, I need to find these photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my hand was in that patch of sunlight, I'm certain there was someone
telling me the shot wouldn't turn out. I went ahead anyway, and have been
experimenting with light, shadow, and colour ever since. Why? I've used
photography to document events, people, and places — as most have — but why
fiddle with it, why play with and push its boundaries?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- My Dad had an interest in photography and owned a Pentax SLR along with four
or five lenses. His youngest brother was a professional photographer, but I
rarely saw him as he lived in England. My father was strictly a portrait
photographer.  He would often say that a photo needs a subject, and would
offer this advice whenever I pointed my camera at some random landscape.
Practically every shot my Dad took has a person in its borders. My
experimentation with photography wasn't learned, nor was it ever a shared
experience. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each shutter release records one face of an infinitely-faceted truth. I've
always been eager to unveil which facet the camera has captured. Digital
cameras immediately reward that anticipation, for better or for worse, but I
still feel it. I've also never lost the desire to influence which truth the
camera records. That desire is partly one of control (through manual exposure,
for example), but also a desire to introduce a little randomness, such as by
shooting with a manual lens. In this way, each shutter release also results in
a delightful surprise, yet one which I've heavily influenced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photography for me is a desire to record a truth, to play with that truth, but
also to experience joy witnessing a surprising take on that same truth. These
desires lead me and others to find beauty in the unexpected — people who love
pictures of decay, for example — or find a unique way to represent beauty that
is more conventional. Photography can then be thought of as part
problem-solving using science and creativity, and part serendipity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, problem-solving using science (math, really) and creativity can
be used to describe software development, something I've explored and enjoyed
about as long as I've explored photography.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>First post</title><link href="//istevens.github.io/daily250/first-post.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-08-29T14:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ian Stevens</name></author><id>tag:istevens.github.io,2016-08-29:daily250/first-post.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past April I ended a contracting gig I'd been on for two-and-a-half years
so that I could spend the summer with my then six-month-old son. Around the
same time, I bought a compact mirrorless digital camera to supplement my hefty
and neglected DSLR. After daily practice with my new camera, I decided to
continue the trend and try to take at least one picture every day. Several
months later, I'm still on track and my photography is much-improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I wondered which other activity could benefit from daily
practice. Writing seemed like an obvious choice, requiring limited tools and a
small time commitment. My daily writing regimen has three restrictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write and publish at least 250 words on a topic decided that day,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write with limited &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006s5dp"&gt;repetition and deviation&lt;/a&gt; from the topic, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with my photography, I want to create good pieces, but good pieces every day
is not a requirement. Most of what I write will be absolute garbage, as
evidenced by this first post. Most people reading my writing won't find it
interesting. That's OK, I'm not writing for them —&amp;nbsp;I'm writing for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope is that writing will become easier and more enjoyable. As a child I was
fond of writing, but these days my writing is limited to business contexts and
trying to cram thoughts into &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/istevens"&gt;140 characters on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. Fun, sometimes, but not expressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's hoping that future attempts don't need sentences like these to pad out
the length requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>